good morning my name is Eli how can you
please tell me your full name yes my
name is Emma Martinez Hayes and what
should I call you just Emma's fine okay
Emma in this first part I'd like to ask
you some questions about yourself let's
talk about what you do do you work or
are you a student I work I am an
entrepreneur so I have an online
Language Academy and I create content
for that Language Academy I also teach
languages I teach English and Spanish so
I have a few different job positions but
yes I work and of course part of being
an entrepreneur is learning so I have to
study a lot as well um how many hours a
week do you study for roughly I would
say it depends on the week if I have
more work if I have a lot of work then
I'll probably study maybe four to 5
hours 1 hour a day I will dedicate to
reading or watching videos or podcasts
about how I can improve in my job but my
main focus is is work um do you think
you will continue this work for a long
time yes I I believe I'll continue this
work because I'm trying to create
something that can sustain myself and my
family in the future so I hope that I
will be doing this for a long time and
I'm that's why I'm studying and working
in order to make sure that this business
and yes everything that I'm creating can
last a long time let's move on let's
talk about teachers do you remember your
teachers from primary school I remember
a few I remember a few of them not all
of them but I did have a few teachers
that were very special to me did you
have a favorite teacher I did have a
favorite teacher she was my kindergarten
teacher yes and did you want to be a
teacher when you were younger I thought
about being a teacher and I think that's
because I'm the oldest of five siblings
so I had the just from a very young age
I had the role of like the oldest the
teacher the leader so I think that
conditioned me being a teacher now so
yes I wanted to be a teacher and I
actually used to play teacher and
student with my brothers and sisters so
I was the teacher and they were students
what kind of teachers do you prefer to
have I think the best teachers are
empathetic so they listen to students
and are very understanding with students
and always give students space to speak
especially if we're talking about
language learning I think that my
preferred way of learning and teaching
languages is through practice instead of
lect leing students so I never want to
just lecture my
students well let's talk about languages
what languages do you speak I speak
English Spanish and Portuguese and I'm
learning French right and have you ever
learned any foreign languages in school
technically Spanish but the US system is
not the best for foreign languages so
they don't have they don't put much
weight on learning languages
unfortunately here in Spain there's more
weight so you know kids from a very
young age have to learn either well they
have to learn English and French and in
the US we don't have that do you think
it's difficult to learn a new language I
think it's difficult to learn a new
language and I think it's more difficult
for some people than others some people
just have a natural skill when it comes
to speaking and learning languages and
acquiring languages and I think you just
have to to know what your learning style
is and what your strengths are as a
learner as a student but in general I do
think that languages are hard to learn
because they're very complex and there
are so many different accents so you
know you if you're learning British
English you're going to hear a lot of
different phrases that don't exist in
the
US why do you think there are some
people I guess like yourself that enjoy
learning lots and lots of languages
yeah I think it for me it's a challenge
it's a challenge to make your brain
rewire your brain to think a different
way and have contact with different
experiences and different perspectives
and I think that people who know more
than one language can connect with more
people from all over the world just for
the fact that they can speak with
different people and you can always make
other people feel more more comfortable
when you speak their language okay we're
going to move on to part two and in this
part I'm going to give you a topic and
I'd like you to talk about it for one to
two minutes before you talk you'll have
one minute to think about what you're
going to say and you can make some notes
if you wish do you understand yes okay
your one minute starts now looks like
you might be ready to go yeah I
am so all right all right I'll just I'll
just introduce you okay all right
remember you have 1 to two minutes for
this so don't worry if I stop you I'll
tell you when the time is up can you
start speaking now please yes so the
picture that I want to describe that
makes me happy is a picture of my two
dogs Bruno and Joel and we're by a lake
here in Seville and this is our nightly
walk so this is where we go on a walk
every night and in the picture I'm
holding a ball and both of them are
fixated with their eyes on the ball
because they're obsessed and they love
playing with balls so this picture makes
me happy because I know how happy it
makes them to go to this park that I
take them to every night they love
chasing after the ball and after a long
day of work it clears my mind to go on
walks with them and even if a lot of
times I don't want to go outside because
I'm tired it's my responsib ability to
take them out so every time I take them
out I just feel calm and relaxed and
when I come back from our walks I always
just am able to have my dinner and go to
bed with a clear mind and I just love
watching them run and play and they
always bring me a lot of Happiness just
to see how free they are and and how
happy and how much love they receive
because both of them are are rescue dogs
so they were abandoned here in Seville
and we me and my partner found them on
the street and rescued them so just
thinking of how we got them and how
happy they are now makes me happy as a
dog mom so yes and have you shown this
photo to other people yes so I took this
picture with out my partner so I showed
him this picture when when I got home
and I sent the picture to my mom as well
Okay so we've been talking about a photo
that makes you happy and I'd like to
discuss with you one or two more general
questions are related to this let's
consider first of all um the emotions
that can be brought up from photographs
so you mentioned how this photo of your
dogs made you feel incredibly happy why
is it that photos can conjure up such
powerful emotions in us I think because
we can well if we took the the photo we
can go back to that place that moment
when the photo was taken and we can
understand the emotion or remember the
emotion that we had in that moment and
if it's a photo taken by someone else we
can analyze the photo and think about it
in how we would feel in that moment or
observe the photo and it might have
different effects on
us um and what what kind of um special
events in somebody's life do you think
it's important to have photos of I would
say weddings definitely weddings maybe
birthdays birthdays especially like
maybe 10 years 15 years old 20 years old
just kind of like the
markers um what else graduations
definitely yeah why is it important to
take photos of these events so that we
can have
a memory forever and share with our
future generations with our kids with
our grandkids and to reflect on what our
life was like when we were younger in
that point in our life so we used to
take a lot of photos with film and now I
guess most photos are digital do you
think that's changed the way that we
take photos and the way that we store
these memories yeah I think that people
probably take a lot more pictures now
than ever and people probably take a lot
more maybe kind of useless or mundane
pictures like their morning breakfast or
their morning coffee or selfies you know
like I think before probably people took
well more useful pictures to capture a
particular moment or a particular
landscape and now maybe it's a little
bit more just not as artistic I guess
yeah why is that why do you think
nowadays we take fewer artistic photos
um and we take probably in general more
photos of ourselves and like you
mentioned our breakfast I think probably
because social media has made us a
little bit more
egocentric and care a lot more about our
appearance and how we look to the rest
of the world how we seem and also
because it's just we're just we have
more possibility to do it to take
pictures all the time so well we just do
it it's possible so let's go for it yeah
let's move on let's talk about
creativity more broadly do you think
creativity is something that can be
taught or is it something that some of
us have and some of us have more of it I
don't know if I would say creativity can
be taught I think creativity can be
developed so I think that if we're
talking about school in the school
system we could put more emphasis on art
classes and just not necessarily telling
kids how they need to paint or how they
need to draw but giving them ideas and
letting them run with those ideas and
have a little bit more freedom with
their creativity so I wouldn't say that
it can it should and can be taught I do
think it's true that there as I said
with languages some people just have
different talents so some people have a
talent for language some people have a
talent for art some people have a talent
for math some for dance so sure some
people have more creativity than others
but I think all people can be creative
if they're given space to develop
creativity do you think it's harder to
have that space and to to develop
creativity when you're older I think it
is because as we get older we start
developing like thoughts about ourselves
so for example if I'm someone who I
don't feel like an artistic person
person as I get older I might say well I
just don't paint I can't paint I don't
know how so those are just boundaries
that we put on ourselves and also as we
get older we have less time so our
priority is probably not going to be
artistic or creative it's probably work
and family so I do think with time it's
harder to develop creativity in terms of
the selft talk and the boundary
um the the things that we say to each to
ourselves where say hey I'm not an
artistic person I'm someone that can't
paint um what's a way to combat that
behavior I think it's really hard
because a lot of these thoughts happen
when we're not paying attention but I
think the key is when you are paying
attention to stop and say hey that's not
true and also probably just working with
a psychologist like working with a
therapist probably to work through those
thoughts those negative thoughts about
ourselves and journaling too could help
having a diary writing down your
thoughts okay thank you very much that
is the end of the speaking test thank
you okay wonderful speaking test so nice
really good it's funny I I found myself
kind of really especially in part three
stopping to kind of focus on the fact
that it was a test and starting to spend
more time thinking about what you were
saying which is is always a good sign if
the examiner kind of loses track of the
language and starts paying attention to
the content yeah and I'm I was thinking
during the test this is really difficult
because on top of like having to focus
on having correct vocabulary and grammar
these are deep questions like these are
actually Phil philosophical questions
yes particularly in part three right
yeah yes so how did you feel doing this
test so I felt very good I think the
questions were interesting and I know
that you know during every test the
questions will be different depending on
the examiner but I thought the questions
were thought-provoking and they were
they were fun to answer yeah totally
sometimes they questions that you've
never really considered in your first
language and so to answer in the
language that you're learning is
particularly difficult right now you
mentioned in part one that you are in
fact a language teacher you're a content
creator you've got a YouTube channel I
believe you're also a podcast host could
you tell us a little bit about you know
all of these Endeavors your
entrepreneurial side yeah thank yeah so
I do have a YouTube channel and on my
YouTube channel I share my podcast and
my podcast is called Emma's language
Journal so this is just a place where I
share my tips and motivation to learn
languages and I also talk to other
language Learners and ask for their
experiences we talk about traveling and
life and living in different cultures I
think a big part of learning languages
is that kind connection with culture so
that's why I live in Spain I love the
Spanish language and I love the culture
here so I tried to share a little bit
about travel language culture and help
language Learners achieve their goal of
fluency and I also have a Language
Academy and we are a team of five
teachers we're all bilingual we're all
certified and we offer private and group
lessons for language learners for
English and Spanish Learners right for
English and Spanish Learners so people
learning English people learning Spanish
exactly so for example if somebody were
watching this speaking test and thinking
well I would like to do a test with Emma
or one of the other language teachers is
that the kind of thing they could do
through your Academy definitely yeah
definitely we have teachers with
experience in testing so for sure we can
prepare classes about about test
preparation right now um you're a native
English speaker you're also a native
Spanish speaker am I right yes kind of
okay tell me a bit about that yeah it
gets a little bit tricky so I'm Mexican
American my family is from Mexico I was
born in the US but when I was growing up
I spoke Spanglish in my household so
when I was Spanish and English yeah
you'll notice a lot of Mexican people
who live in the US speak Spanglish
because it's just mixing culture mixing
language so that's what happened to me
so when I was in elementary school they
put me in ESL class because my last name
Martinez what my appearance also because
well I spoke Spanglish so I took ESL
classes in in elementary school and then
I think they realized like no actually
she speaks English and she understands
English so they took me out of ESL and
what happened is that because I only had
contact with Spanish through my family I
just didn't develop a very deep Spanish
level so I had to actually study Spanish
in University to become really really
fluent like the fluency that I have
today is because I actually did have to
study so that's why I say kind of I have
the level that I have today because I've
always had contact with Spanish but it's
a little bit tricky and people who are
from different cultures and live in like
an English-speaking country can
understand that that like just you lose
something from both cultures right like
we have this phrase in Spanish
that's yeah not from here or from there
somewh yeah that's just kind of the
struggle that's the mixed person
struggle so I'm sure a lot of your
viewers can relate to that and so when
you started learning Portuguese that was
a totally new language for you then yes
but Portuguese is quite similar to
Spanish well Brazilian Portuguese
European Portuguese is very difficult
but Brazilian Portuguese is like Spanish
so because I already studied Spanish it
was quite easy for me to learn
Portuguese right okay interesting yes
and um did you also mention that you're
learning French at the moment yeah I
started two weeks
ago right so if you're learning a
language I take it French is from
scratch from from elementary level
what's your approach to language
learning now considering that you know
you reached such a high level of English
Spanish Portuguese has that kind of
played a role and shaped how you're
going to learn French definitely
definitely so I already made a video
about like what I'm doing now as a
French learner but first I'm learning
the pronunciation and having speaking
practice which I have Elementary level
so I can't speak but I'm taking classes
from the beginning and what I see a lot
of students do is from the beginning
start studying grammar and that's kind
of boring and then you lose your
motivation and you want to give up and
so that's something that I the mistake
that I don't want to make this time
around I want to start with speaking and
pronunciation also because I know French
pronunciation is very very difficult so
I know that I need to work on that from
the beginning so that I can at least
understand people yes and then from the
understanding you're going to be hearing
more vocabulary and then hopefully
fingers crossed you'll start producing
it yeah right definitely great anything
else that you would like me to ask you
before we continue no I don't yeah I
don't think so maybe you could ask like
because we both lived in Spain so we
could talk a little bit about that that
sounds like a great idea so now you're
in Spain I think you said you were in
seevilla or Seville um I was actually
living in Spain for a long time in
Barcelona how have you found the
transition from going from Seattle to
living in in in Spain I find that is
such a comfortable city right so it's
not a huge City like Barcelona Barcelona
is huge and Madrid is huge and I'm from
the suburbs in the US so I'm not from
like Seattle downtown you know so I
think that Seville is the perfect size
it's small you can get everywhere
walking or by public
transportation and what I mean you know
there's a lot of movement in tourism
that's what I love about life here in
general but it's not overwhelming like
Madrid for example so I found the
transition very comfortable and I love
life here do you see yourself living in
Spain for a long time then now that's
where it gets tricky I love Spain and I
love cevil but my family's so far away
so that's hard I also know that feeling
well as well as living in Spain I also
lived in in China and Ireland and and
it's only recently that I've moved back
to Scotland where my family are based
right yeah and I know it gets even more
complicated when there's um
relationships involved so you mentioned
your partner I imagine he might not be
from Seattle and you might not have
moved together you might have met in
Spain in which case that yeah introduces
a whole new level of complexity right
definitely so we'll see what what the
future tells right we'll see what
happens but for now I'm I'm happy here
in ceville and I can travel freely
between the US and ceville because I
work online so that's the beautiful
thing of working online as well yes and
a great motivator for you to continue
creating all this wonderful content and
for building your business right yeah
definitely great all right a big thank
you for coming on sharing your
experience learning languages and also
for showing students such an amazing I
test there's really so much to learn
from the test that we've done today yeah
good luck guys and make sure to practice
like reading maybe about like not
philosophical stuff but just deeper
stuff you know to be prepared totally
great stuff all right big thank you
thank you bye